Finding Aid for John Harvey Kellogg Papers, 1832-1965
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
John Harvey Kellogg Papers 1832-1965, 1874-1943
Kellogg, John Harvey, 1852-1943.
30.5 GB
(in 21 boxes)
19.3 linear feet
Battle Creek, Michigan physician, food scientist, founder of the Battle Creek Sanitarium. Correspondence, student notebooks from University of Michigan and Bellevue Hospital, drafts of speeches and lecture notes, newspaper clippings and scrapbooks, and topical files; include material concerning medical theories and practices, especially matters of diet and hygiene, his work with organizations such as the National Vitality League, Race Betterment Foundation, Battle Creek Three Quarter Century Club, Chicago Workingmen's Home and Medical Mission, and Seventh-Day Adventists; also photographs.
851724 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Gertrude W. Goodwin (Donor No. 3506 ), secretary of the Race Betterment Foundation of Battle Creek, Michigan.
The collection is open for research.
A microfilm edition of the Kellogg papers is also available. The microfilm edition is described in a separate finding aid.
John Harvey Kellogg, born February 26, 1852, earned worldwide acclaim in his lifetime as a health reformer and propagandist, and as head of the Battle Creek Sanitarium. Kellogg is now best known in connection with the line of breakfast cereal products made by the company that bears his name. While John Harvey Kellogg conceived the notion of flaked corn as a healthful morning repast, it was his brother, Will Keith, who turned his hand to the development of the breakfast food company. John Harvey Kellogg was also a skilled surgeon, an editor, and scientist who saw himself as primarily an educator determined to focus public attention on preventive medicine as the means to maintain good health. The main thrust of Kellogg's good health message was that vegetarian diet, regular exercise, fresh air, and sunshine are the keys to a long and vigorous life. Kellogg was a testament to the efficacy of his principles, living to age ninety-one and working diligently until succumbing to pneumonia on December 14, 1943.
Kellogg's father, a convert to Seventh Day Adventism, moved his family to Battle Creek when John Harvey was age four; thus the young Kellogg grew up well versed in the health reform principles of the Adventists. Many of these tenets, especially regarding vegetarianism and temperance, were elements of Kellogg's mature thinking on healthful "biologic living." Kellogg, an 1875 graduate of Bellevue Hospital Medical College, brought a solid training in orthodox medicine to his health reform efforts. In this, he differed from most earlier health reformers, whose systems often lacked grounding in science. Kellogg made repeated trips to Europe to keep abreast of developments in medicine, surgery, and physiology in order to buttress the scientific foundations which supported his health teachings.
Upon completion of his medical training, Kellogg returned as medical superintendent of the Adventists' Western Health Reform Institute in Battle Creek. Kellogg's vigorous efforts as a promoter and publicist soon brought the Battle Creek Sanitarium (as the Institute was renamed in 1876) to national prominence as "a place where people learn to stay well." Kellogg used the Sanitarium as a testing ground for the application of his "Battle Creek idea" on the effect of diet, exercise, correct posture, fresh air, and rest on the health and fitness of individuals. The program did enhance health. Kellogg and the Sanitarium prospered, despite policy differences with the Seventh Day Adventists, a 1902 fire which destroyed the building, and receivership debt due to overbuilding, until the 1930s Depression cut down patronage. In good times, Kellogg traded heavily on the celebrity of the Sanitarium's clientele to sell his health reform ideas. In hard times, he relied on the strength of the science which girded his system to keep pushing health. Throughout his sixty-seven year association with the Sanitarium, Kellogg never wavered in his faith in the rectitude of the "Battle Creek idea."
Kellogg was a prolific author and had a ready venue of publication in Good Health, a magazine he edited for nearly seventy years. Kellogg incorporated many of the ideas which appeared first as articles in Good Health into nearly fifty books. Included among them are: Body in Health, Colon Hygiene, New Dietetics, Plain Facts about Sexual Life, Practical Manual of Health and Temperance, and Rational Hydrotherapy. These books manifest Kellogg's efforts to bring the new medical science to the general public. Kellogg also lectured from coast-to-coast touring his message before as large an audience as possible. Finally, Kellogg's dynamic personality attracted disciples to Battle Creek to study at the feet of the master of "rational" medicine; these disciples in turn propagated Kellogg's ideas that medical science pointed to adherence to a vegetarian regimen of moderation as the surest way to good health.
The John Harvey Kellogg papers document the career of a medical doctor and health reformer and advocate. The collection provides telling insight to the operation of the Battle Creek Sanitarium. The papers span the years 1869 to 1965, with the bulk of the materials covering the years 1874 to 1943. Significantly, there are some collected published items in the collection that date as early as 1832. The Kellogg papers consist of correspondence, lectures, notes, memoranda, clippings, scrapbooks, notebooks, photographs, articles, and book manuscripts. These diverse sources provide ample documentation of Kellogg's life, and are an excellent source with which to examine early twentieth-century medicine in general and Kellogg's important innovations in health reform. The collection is also very strong on the development of the Sanitarium and the "Battle Creek idea" of natural health. Kellogg's zealous efforts to proselytize the world at large on the wisdom of the "Battle Creek Idea" are reflected in the papers. Also included are materials relating to his work with organizations such as the National Vitality League, Race Betterment Foundation, Battle Creek Three Quarter Century Club, Chicago Workingmen's Home and Medical Mission, and Seventh-Day Adventists.
The Kellogg collection came to the Michigan Historical Collections in two primary accessions, one in 1962 and another in 1972. Parts of the collection were reprocessed in 1988 prior to the entire collection being microfilmed. The collection is now divided into the following series: Biographical/Personal; Correspondence; Lectures, Speeches, and Related; Notes and Articles; Subject Files (medical missionaries); Clippings/ Scrapbooks; Bound Manuscripts/Published Volumes; and Photographs.
Subjects:
Battle Creek (Mich.); Battle Creek Sanitarium.; Bellevue Hospital.; Chicago Workingmen's Home and Medical Mission.; Depressions--1929--United States.; Food.; Hygiene.; Ireland.; Kellogg, John Harvey, 1852-1943.; Medicine--Michigan--Battle Creek.; National Vitality League.; Physicians--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Prohibition--United States.; Public health--United States.; Race Betterment Foundation.; Physicians--Religious life--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Seventh Day Adventist Church (Battle Creek, Mich.); Three Quarter Century Club (Battle Creek, Mich.); University of Michigan. Medical School.; University of Michigan--Student notebooks.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Battle Creek (Mich.)--Buildings.; Battle Creek (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Battle Creek (Mich.)--Health resorts.; Battle Creek Sanitarium.; Buildings--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Buildings--Illinois--Chicago.; Chicago (Ill.)--Buildings.; Chicago (Ill.)--Missions.; Dwellings--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Families.; Health resorts--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Hospitals--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Interiors.; Kellogg, John Harvey, 1852-1943.; Kellogg family.; Laboratories.; Medicine--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Missions--Illinois--Chicago.; Physical fitness.; Slums.; Women.
Contributors:
Barron, Clarence Walker, 1855-1928.; Boldyreff, W.; Byrd, Richard Evelyn, 1888-1957.; Campbell, B. Hodges.; Edison, Mary Stilwell.; Edison, Thomas A. (Thomas Alva), 1847-1931.; Efromoff, G.; Fisher, Irving, 1867-1947.; Ford, Clara Bryant, 1866-1950.; Ford, Henry, 1863-1947.; LeHand, Margaret.; Liebold, Ernest G., 1884-; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.; Parran, Thomas.; Pavlov, Ivan Petrovich, 1849-1936.; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946.; Pingree, Hazen S., 1840-1901.; Plunckett, Horace.; Pomari, M.; Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison), 1874-1960.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Shaw, Bernard, 1856-1950.; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930.; Tarbell, Ida M. (Ida Minerva), 1857-1944.; Tissier, L.; Tolstoy, Alexandra, 1884-1979.; Tolstoy, Ilga.; Tolstoy, Leo, 1828-1910.; Van Shaick, Louis J.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Personal/Biographical
  Biographical/Personal (0.1 linear feet) is a small series drawn from different parts of the collection containing summary information about Kellogg's life as well as some of the awards he received throughout his career.
  - Autobiographical and Biographical Notes, 2 folders; .PDF and .ZIP files (Box 1)
  - Awards, Citations, etc., .PDF and .ZIP files
    - Legal size (Box 1)
    - Large Format (Box 21)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (2 linear feet; 1875-1948) documents Kellogg's many interests and the operation of the sanitarium. Correspondents in the collection include C. W. Barron, Richard E. Byrd, Mary G. Edison, Irving Fisher, Clara J. Ford, Henry Ford, Margaret LeHand, Ernest G. Liebold, Chase S. Osborn, I. P. Pavlov, Gifford Pinchot, Hazen Pingree, Sir Horace Plunckett, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Franklin D. Roosevelt, Bernard Shaw, William Howard Taft, Ida Tarbell, Alexandra Tolstoi, Leo Tolstoi, Ilga Tolstoi, and Louis J. Van Shaick.
  - 1875-1899, .PDF and .ZIP files (Box 1)
  - 1900-1918, .PDF and .ZIP files (Box 1)
  - 1919, .PDF and .ZIP files (Box 1)
  - 1920, .PDF and .ZIP files (Box 1)
  - 1921, .PDF and .ZIP files (Box 1)
  - 1922-1923, .PDF and .ZIP files (Box 1)
  - 1924-1925, .PDF and .ZIP files (Box 1)
  - 1926-1929, .PDF and .ZIP files (Box 1)
  - 1930-1932, .PDF and .ZIP files (Box 1)
  - 1933-1934, .PDF and .ZIP files (Box 1)
  - January-June 1935, .PDF and .ZIP files (Box 1)
  - July-December, 1935, .PDF and .ZIP files (Box 2)
  - 1936, .PDF and .ZIP files (Box 2)
  - 1937, .PDF and .ZIP files (Box 2)
  - 1938, .PDF and .ZIP files (Box 2)
  - 1939, .PDF and .ZIP files (Box 2)
  - 1940, .PDF and .ZIP files (Box 2)
  - 1941, .PDF and .ZIP files (Box 3)
  - 1942-1948, 3 folders; .PDF and .ZIP files (Box 3)
  - Undated, .PDF and .ZIP files (Box 3)
  - Retakes (digital and microfilm versions)
    - 1933, .PDF and .ZIP files
    - 1936-1938, .PDF and .ZIP files
    - 1938-1941, .PDF and .ZIP files
- Lectures, Speeches, and Related Materials
  The researcher will find the fullest development of Kellogg's thinking on any specific topic in the Lectures, Speeches, and Related Materials series (4.5 linear feet; 1875-1943). This series is arranged chronologically with each presentation listed.
  - 1875, 1884, .PDF and .ZIP files
    - What is disease? February 14, 1875 (Box 3)
      (graduation essay)
    - How to live a century February 15, 1884 (Box 3)
      (Sanitarium Lectures)
  - June-July 1891, .PDF and .ZIP files
    - Nature's Method of Defending the Body Against Disease June 5, 1891 (Box 3)
    - How nature defends the body against disease June 19, 1891 (Box 3)
    - Health is contagious July 10, 1891 (Box 3)
  - October-November 1891, .PDF and .ZIP files
    - A Twentieth Century Doctor October 2, 1891 (Box 3)
    - How Not to Take Cold October 16, 1891 (Box 3)
    - The Weather October 23, 1891 (Box 3)
    - Physical Influence of the Weather October 31, 1891 (Box 3)
    - The Weather (Pt. II) November 12, 1891 (Box 3)
  - April 1892, .PDF and .ZIP files
    - How to Dress Hygienically January 14, 1892 (Box 3)
    - Attitudes, 1892 April 11, April 10 1892 (Box 3)
    - Swedish Gymnastics April 19, 1892 (Box 3)
  - August and December 1892, .PDF and .ZIP files
    - Dreams August 19, 1892 (Box 3)
    - On Mexico December 22, 1892 (Box 3)
  - January-June 1893, .PDF and .ZIP files
    - Mexico January 18, 1893 (Box 3)
    - What is the Soul? April 29, 1893 (Box 3)
    - Relations of the Muscles to Religion June 15, 1893 (Box 3)
  - July-December 1893, .PDF and .ZIP files
    - The House We Live In July 13, 1893 (Box 3)
    - The Human Figure August 3, 1893 (Box 3)
    - On the Hygiene of Dress December 7, 1893 (Box 3)
    - On the Hygiene of Dress (Pt. II) December 14, 1893 (Box 3)
  - 1894, .PDF and .ZIP files
    - The Medical Profession April 29, 1894 (Box 3)
      (an address delivered before the Students' Christian Association, Ann Arbor)
    - Materialism in the Medical Profession October 20, 1894 (Box 3)
  - 1895, .PDF and .ZIP files
    - The Man Wonderful in the House Beautiful January 27, 1895 (Box 3)
    - Medical Missionary College Opening October 1, 1895 (Box 3)
    - Memory (also The Physiology of Memory) October 10, 1895 (Box 3)
  - 1896, .PDF and .ZIP files
    - Religion of the Body January 2, 1896 (Box 3)
    - Twenty Years' Experience in the Non-Alcoholic Treatment of Diseases May 1, 1896 (Box 3)
    - The Cure of Incurables (2 pts.) June 1896 (Box 3)
    - The Weather October 1, 1896 (Box 3)
    - Medical Missionary College Exercises October 15, 1896 (Box 3)
  - 1897, .PDF and .ZIP files
    - Why We are Cripples January 7, 1897 (Box 3)
    - Physical Basis of Faith January 8, 1897 (Box 3)
    - Rational Medicine June 15, 1897 (Box 3)
    - Our Food and How We Digest Them (also labeled From Bread to Brain) July 25, 1897 (Box 3)
    - Common Errors in Diet July 26, 1897 (Box 3)
    - The Quality of Food July 26, 1897 (Box 3)
    - The Dietetic Value of-Fruits circa 1897 (Box 3)
  - 1898
    - Lecture series on fruits, .PDF and .ZIP files
      - Fruits circa 1898 (Box 3)
      - Relation of Fruits to Digestion March 18, 1898 (Box 3)
      - Fruits--Their Digestibility, Uses, etc. April 29, 1898 (Box 3)
      - Fruits--Their Therapeutic Uses May 2, 1898 (Box 3)
      - Fruits--Toxins, etc. May 3, 1898 (Box 3)
      - Fruits--Autointoxication in Relation to Diet May 4, 1898 (Box 3)
      - Fruits--Diet in Disease May 5, 1898 (Box 3)
      - Fruits--Their Relation to Diet May 6, 1898 (Box 3)
      - Fruits--Fruits Cure in Obesity, etc. May 9, 1898 (Box 3)
      - Dietetics--Fruits circa 1898 (Box 3)
    - Lecture series on topic of fevers October 1898, undated 1898, 13 lectures (in 2 folders); .PDF and .ZIP files (Box 3)
    - Lecture series on Physiology, .PDF and .ZIP files
      - Physiology (lecture no. 29 (Box 3)
      - Physiology (lecture no. 35) (Box 3)
      - Physiology (lecture no. 36) (Box 3)
      - Physiology (lecture no. 38) (Box 3)
      - Physiology (lecture no. 39) (Box 3)
      - Physiology (lecture no. 40) (Box 3)
      - Physiology (lecture no. 41) (Box 3)
    - Articles on the Nut Diet, .PDF and .ZIP files
      - A Growing Interest in Nut Diet (Box 3)
      - A great waste (Box 3)
      - Appreciative words about nut foods (Box 3)
      - Miss Henderson's Illness (Box 3)
      - Saved a Baby's Life (Box 3)
      - Bicycle trip on nut foods (Box 3)
      - Nuts and gas production (Box 3)
      - Nut Butter in India (Box 3)
      - The Peanut, Botanically (Box 3)
      - Pistache Nuts (Box 3)
      - A Curious Old Custom (Box 3)
      - Chestnuts and Pine Nuts (Box 3)
      - Nuts as foods for Working People (Box 3)
      - Six Years' Experience with Fruits and Nuts (Box 3)
      - The Pecan as a Food (Box 3)
    - Sanitarium Parlor Lectures, .PDF and .ZIP files
      - Hygiene, lecture given by H. S. Tanner January 5, 1898 (Box 3)
      - How to Get Well Quick January 27, 1898 (Box 3)
      - Some Popular Fallacies in Relation to Things Medical February 3, 1898 (Box 3)
      - Foods--Fruits and Starches March 31, 1898 (Box 3)
      - Foods--Fruits and Nuts April 7, 1898 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous arranged by date, .PDF and .ZIP files
      - Appendicitis February 1898 (Box 3)
      - Practical Reason for Withholding Prescriptions of Alcohol February 2, 1898 (Box 3)
      - The Nature of Drink Habit February 2, 1898 (Box 3)
      - New Experiments Respecting the Effect of Alcohol upon the Muscles February 2, 1898 (Box 3)
      - Medical Dietetics--Food--Source of Energy March 14, 1898 (Box 3)
      - Report of Staten Island Branch Sanitarium August 31, 1898 (Box 3)
      - Electric Light Sweat Baths October 26, 1898 (Box 3)
      - The Electric Light or Radiant Heat Bath November 30, 1898 (Box 3)
      - The Nebraska Sanitarium December 1898 (Box 3)
      - The Electro-Hydric or Electro-Thermal Bath December 1, 1898 (Box 3)
    - Fragmentary, .PDF and .ZIP files
      - Untitled (diet and fruits) (Box 3)
      - Fruit Diet (Box 3)
      - Early Observation of the Disease Now Known as Friedrich's Atoxia (Box 3)
      - Unphysiological Advice (Box 3)
  - 1899, .PDF and .ZIP files
    - Portland Sanitarium January 1899 (Box 3)
    - Rational Medicine January 24, 1899 (Box 3)
    - St. Helena Sanitarium January 31, 1899 (Box 3)
    - The Physical Basis of Faith October 3, 1899 (Box 3)
    - The Medical Missionary Work and the Gospel Ministry December 22, 1897 (Box 3)
    - God's Design in Establishing Sanitariums December 22, 1899 (Box 3)
    - The Physician's Work a Cure of Souls circa 1899 (Box 3)
    - Dangers and Duties of the Physician and the Medical Missionary circa 1899 (Box 3)
  - January-February 1900, .PDF and .ZIP files
    - Auto-Intoxication, or self-poisoning January 15, 1900 (Box 3)
      (lecture given by A. B. Olsen)
    - Pneumonia--symptoms, etc. (clinic) February 2, 1900 (Box 3)
    - The treatment of pneumonia (clinic) February 4, 1900 (Box 3)
    - Treatment of pneumonia, February 6, February 7, February 8, February 12, February 13 February 15, 1900 (6 pts.) (Box 3)
  - April-July 1900, .PDF and .ZIP files
    - What is the Natural Food of Man? April 16, 1900 (Box 3)
    - Typhoid Fever April 27, 1900, May 6, 1900 (2 pts.) (Box 3)
    - Dress Reform Talk June 6, 1900 (Box 3)
    - Talk given at Students' Clinic June 17, 1900 (Box 3)
    - Electricity (Talk given at Students' Clinic) July 2, 1900 (Box 3)
    - Dress Reform Talk July 7, 1900, July 8, 1900 (2 pts.) (Box 3)
  - September-November 1900, .PDF and .ZIP files
    - Branch Sanitarium and Their Purposes September 24, 1900 (Box 3)
    - Medical Students' Commencement September 26, 1900 (Box 3)
    - How Nature Fights Disease September 27, 1900 (Box 3)
    - How We Can Aid Nature in the Struggle Against Disease October 4, 1900 (Box 3)
    - The Return to Nature October 11, 1900 (Box 3)
    - The Evolution of Rational Medicine October 18, 1900, October 25, 1900 (2 pts.) (Box 3)
    - Getting Well November 1, 1900 (Box 3)
  - January-May 1901, .PDF and .ZIP files
    - Chronic Intestinal Indigestion January 10, 1901 (Box 3)
    - Causes and Cure of Chronic Intestinal Inactivity January 17, 1901 (Box 3)
    - How to be Strong January 24, 1901, January 31, 1901 (2 pts.) (Box 3)
    - Address to Medical Students March 30, 1901 (Box 3)
    - Stereopticon Views and Reports of Sanitariums April 10, 1901 (Box 3)
    - Divine Healing April 16, 1901 (Box 3)
    - The Power of Nature May 2, 1901 (Box 3)
    - Medical Gymnastics May 10, 1901 (Box 3)
  - August-October 1901, .PDF and .ZIP files
    - The Circulation of the Blood August 19, 1901 (Box 4)
    - Student's Clinic (constipation) August 25, 1901 (Box 4)
    - Health Talks (constipation) September 9, 1901 (Box 4)
    - Health Talks (to nurses) September 9, 1901 (Box 4)
    - Follies of Fashionable Life September 12, 1901, September 19, 1901 (2 pts) (Box 4)
    - Muscular Movements October 3, 1901 (Box 4)
    - Talks to Medical Class (Sophomores) on topic of exercise October 1901 (7 pts.) (Box 4)
  - November-December 1901, .PDF and .ZIP files
    - The Liver November 14, 1901 (Box 4)
    - Physiological-Therapeutics--What is Disease? (talks to Junior Medical Students), 1901 December 10, 1901 December 11, 1901 December 12, 1901 December 9 (4 pts.) (Box 4)
    - Chapter on Therapeutics, etc. December 9, 1901 (Box 4)
      (probably used as background for therapeutics talks)
    - Disease--Defenses of the Body December 13, 1901 (Box 4)
  - January 1902 undated 1902, .PDF and .ZIP files
    - Health Food Fakirs circa 1902 (Box 4)
    - Health-Getting and Health-Keeping January 20, 1902 (Box 4)
  - February-May 1902, .PDF and .ZIP files
    - Minutes of mass meetings held in Battle following fire that destroyed the Sanitarium; also corner stone laying remarks (Box 4)
  - August-October 1902, .PDF and .ZIP files
    - Home-coming, Getting Well, etc. August 21, 1902 (Box 4)
    - Opening Exercises of the American Missionary College September 25, 1902 (Box 4)
    - Physiological Therapeutics September 26, 1902 (Box 4)
    - Gynecology. Urinary diseases--causes of September 30, 1902 (Box 4)
    - Hydriatic Treatment of Inflammatory Conditions October 26, 1902 (Box 4)
  - October 1902 Lectures on Gynecology, .PDF and .ZIP files
    - Weakness of Women--Causes of October 1, 1902 (Box 4)
    - Human figure October 2, 1902 (Box 4)
    - Pelvic Diseases--Causes of October 3, 1902 (Box 4)
    - Pelvic Diseases--Direct Causes October 6, 1902 (Box 4)
    - Neurasthenia October 20, 1902 (Box 4)
  - October-November 1902 Lectures on Physiological Therapeutics, .PDF and .ZIP files
    - Position October 1, 1902 (Box 4)
    - Wall--Training October 21, 1902 (Box 4)
    - Exercise for Invalids October 22, 1902 (Box 4)
    - Chair and Floor Training October 23, 1902 (Box 4)
    - Exercise--Kind and Amount October 28, 1902, October 30, 1902 (2 pts.) (Box 4)
    - The Defenses of the Body, November 5 1902, November 7 1902, November 11, 1902 (3 pts.) (Box 4)
  - January 1903 Lectures on Thermotherapy (2 pts.), .PDF and .ZIP files (Box 4)
  - January-March 1903 Lectures on Dietetics (14 pts.), .PDF and .ZIP files (Box 4)
  - March-May 1903, .PDF and .ZIP files
    - The Significance of Enteroptosis February-March 1903, undated (Box 4)
    - Pelvic Inflammation March 13, 1903 (Box 4)
    - Sanitarium Talk to Patients (on returning from the West) April 16, 1903 (Box 4)
    - New Sanitarium Dedication Exercises May 31, 1903 (Box 4)
  - July-August 1903, .PDF and .ZIP files
    - Lectures to Post Graduates on Electrotherapeutics July 1903 (5 pts.) (Box 4)
    - Electricity, or Lightning July 30, 1903 (Box 4)
    - Getting Well August 6, 1903 (Box 4)
    - Flesh Foods August 13, 1903 (Box 4)
    - Graduating Exercises of the Sanitarium Training School for Missionary Nurses August 24, 1903 (Box 4)
    - Student's Clinic August 25, 1903 (Box 4)
    - Dietetics. Hypopepsia August 31, 1903 (Box 4)
  - September-November 1903, .PDF and .ZIP files
    - Healthful Dishes, and Diet for the Sick September 1903 (Box 4)
    - Diet for Hypo's September 3, 1903 (Box 4)
    - Opening Exercises of the American Medical Missionary College September 23, 1903 (Box 4)
    - Hydrotherapy November 5, 1903 (Box 4)
    - Good Health for 1904 November 6, 1903 (Box 4)
    - The Sanitarium Method; a stereopticon Lecture November 19, 1903 (Box 4)
    - Nature Cures November 22, 1903 (Box 4)
    - The Principles of Medical Missionary Work as Carried on in our Sanitariums (address given by Dr. David Paulson) November 30, 1903 (Box 4)
  - January-February 1904: Nurses Post-Graduate lectures on General Diseases, (7 pts.), .PDF and .ZIP files (Box 4)
  - January-February 1904, .PDF and .ZIP files
    - Electrotherapy January 7, 1904 (Box 4)
    - Dietetic class (Nurses Post-Graduate lecture) January 10, 1904 (Box 4)
    - Pneumonia February 16, 1904 (Box 4)